in this video we're going to talk about
the formation of a cyanohydrin from a
ketone
so let's begin with the overall
chemical reaction
so here we have a ketone specifically
acetone
and we're going to react it with hcn
hydrogen cyanide
the ketone functional group will be
converted into a hydroxyl group
with the addition of a nitrile group
and so this molecule
is called
a cyanohydrin
now let's talk about the mechanism by
which
we can get this product
so the first thing we're going to do is
we're going to use
excess cyanide
and a small amount of hcl
some of the cyanide ions will pick up a
proton from hcl
turning into
hydrogen cyanide
and we're going to get the chloride ion
so keep in mind we have a large amount
of cyanide
a small amount of hcl and so we're going
to get a small amount of hcn
so starting with the ketone functional
group
which
the oxygen has two lone pairs
we're going to take
the cyanide ion
and as the nucleophile it's going to be
attracted
to the carbonyl group
keep in mind the carbon atom has a
partial positive charge
whereas the cyanide ion has a negative
charge so they're attracted to each
other
so as the nucleophile attacks the
carbonyl carbon
the pi electrons in this double bond
are going to break and they're going to
be pulled back to oxygen because oxygen
is more electronegative than carbon
and so what we're going to get right now
is
an alkoxide ion
with
a nitro group attached to it
now in the next step
the alkoxide ion is going to be a prot
let me say that again the alkoxide ion
will be protonated by hcn
so it's going to grab a hydrogen
regenerating the cyanide ion
and so the end result
is
a cyanohydrin molecule
and so that's the mechanism for this
reaction